# Nicholas Hoyt Front-End Developer

Address: Urbana, Illinois, USA Phone:
Portfolio: <a href="https://nicholashoyt.com/portfolio">https://nicholashoyt.com/portfolio</a> Email:

With over 20 years of front-end development and user interface design experience, my professionalism and track record of success are based on choosing technologies that are both maintainable and understandable by other developers, and on maximizing user experience by focusing on users' goals in relation to product features.

## **Experience**

## University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Sept. 2005 – present

Serve as lead user experience designer, user interface designer, and front-end developer of web applications and browser tools focused on web accessibility evaluation.

Several of these tools have been adopted by the University of Illinois and other large university systems (e.g. Penn. State, Indiana University, Ohio State, University of Iowa) as their tools of choice for web accessibility evaluation.

- Designed and co-developed the 'Functional Accessibility Evaluator', a web application that spiders websites and produces site-wide reports on WCAG compliance.
- Designed and co-developed the 'Alnspector for Firefox' browser extension, which does the same type of evaluation as the Functional Accessibility Evaluator for a single web page.
- Designed and developed two additional browser extensions: 'SkipTo Landmarks & Headings' and 'Page Structure'.
- Designed and co-developed the 'A11yFirst plugins for CKEditor', which provide proactive guidance for accessible authoring, including proper heading structure and text alternatives for images.
- Designed and co-developed the 'Accessibility Bookmarklets', easily installable in any browser.

#### Independent Contractor, Chicago, IL

Aug. 1999 - Sept. 2005

As owner and principal consultant of Web UI, Inc., provided software design and development services with a focus on user interface design and front-end development for various clients, including ABN AMRO, Accenture, Allstate Insurance, Bank One, Fidelity Investments, HOLT Value Associates and the Illinois Institute of Technology.

- Updated the 'Contribution Calculator' previously designed and developed for Fidelity Investments.
- · Authored an ebook on XML and XSLT development for internal use by Accenture developers.
- Designed a web application for use by call center representatives at Allstate Insurance.
- · Designed the user interface of a Java application for use by financial portolio managers for HOLT Value Associates.

#### Fidelity Investments, Boston, MA

Aug. 1997 - Aug. 1999

Served as lead interaction designer in the redesign of 'NetBenefits', a web application providing retirement savings account access to over one million customers. Improved the user experience through contextual inquiry, task flow analysis and usability testing.

Designed and developed retirement investing tools for 401k.com, Fidelity's website for institutional investors. Tools included the 'Contribution Calculator', 'Withdrawal Calculator' and 'Take Home Pay Calculator'.

# Nicholas Hoyt

## **Education**

B.A. in Computer Science, University of Massachusetts Boston, 1991 Summa cum laude

Introduction to Programming in Pascal, Harvard Extension School, 1988 Grade: A

Jazz Composition & Arranging major, Berklee College of Music, Boston, MA Seven full-time semesters, 1981–1984, GPA of 3.85/4.0

## **Skills**

## Front-End Development

- · JavaScript (ES6 and later), HTML, CSS, DOM scripting and event handling
- Responsive design, web components, custom element authoring, Lit, React
- · WebExtensions API

## User Interface Design

- · Experience with creating wireframes, interactive prototypes, user stories
- · Usability testing and accessibility evaluation

## Web Accessibility

- · WCAG requirements
- · ARIA Authoring Practices, ARIA in HTML

### Web Development

- · Git, Node.js, npm, Babel, webpack, Rollup, Gulp, Sass
- Python, Django, XML/XSLT

#### Resources

#### **Installation Links**

- Alnspector for Firefox
- A11yFirst plugins for CKEditor
- SkipTo Landmarks & Headings for Chrome
- SkipTo Landmarks & Headings for Firefox
- Page Structure for Firefox
- · Accessibility Bookmarklets

#### **Code Repositories**

- Alnspector for Firefox
- SkipTo Landmarks & Headings
- Page Structure
- Accessibility Bookmarklets
- Copy Page Link